Finding Aid for Homer Ferguson Papers
Bentley Historical Library
Homer Ferguson Papers
1939-1976
Bentley Historical Library
Ferguson, Homer, 1888-1982
85187 Aa 2 Ac
26 linear feet
1 oversize folder
35 phonograph records
769 MB (online)
Republican U.S. Senator from Michigan, U.S. Ambassador to the Philippines; files relating to his various career responsibilities, photographs, sound recordings.
The Homer Ferguson collection (donor no. 1761 ) was donated in 1983 by Mrs. Amy Ferguson Beltz, executrix of the Ferguson estate.
The collection is open for research. Digitized audio files are currently available only in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
Homer Ferguson, Wayne County circuit judge, United States senator, ambassador to the Philippines, and judge on the United States Court of Military Appeals, was born on February 25, 1888 in Harrison City, Pennsylvania. He attended the University of Pittsburgh (1910-1911) and received his LL.B. from the University of Michigan in 1913. In the same year, he was admitted to the Michigan Bar and practiced law in the state until 1929.
While serving as circuit court judge for Wayne County (1929-1941), Ferguson achieved fame when he sat as a One-Man grand jury (1939-1941) investigating crime, graft, and corruption in Detroit and Wayne County. Shortly thereafter, in 1942, he was elected as a Republican to the United States Senate and was re-elected in 1948.
Ferguson's fame as a tough investigator grew during his tenure in the senate, when he sat on committees that drew public attention because of the probes and inquiries they initiated. Included among these committees were: Appropriations; Expenditures in the Executive Department; Judiciary; Special Committee Investigating the National Defense Program; and the Joint Committee on the Investigation of the Pearl Harbor Attack. A conservative who was always interested in efficiency in government, the Senator was also appointed to the Hoover Commission on the Reorganization of the Executive Branch of the Government. His interest in international affairs was evident in his long-term participation, both during and after his senatorial career, in the activities of the Inter-Parliamentary Union, a body of representatives from the parliaments of countries around the world that met approximately once a year to study issues of international concern related to law, economics, and world peace.
Shortly after losing his 1954 bid for a third senatorial term, Ferguson became United States Ambassador to the Philippines where he served for thirteen months (1955-1956). He thereupon returned to Washington, D.C., and sat for fifteen years on the United States Court of Military Appeals - the equivalent of the Supreme Court for the armed forces. Though his term expired in 1971, Ferguson continued on as a senior judge and rendered verdicts on various cases for another five years.
In 1976, the judge and his wife of sixty-three years, Myrtle, retired to Grosse Pointe, Michigan. Homer Ferguson died there on December 17, 1982.
Summary Contents List
Circuit Judgeship: One-Man Grand Jury, 1939-1941 -- boxes 1-2
Senate Career, 1942-1954 -- boxes 2-14
Committees -- boxes 2-11
Pearl Harbor-- boxes 8-11
Correspondence -- box 11
Legislative Record -- box 12
Public Addresses -- boxes 12-13
Topical Files -- boxes 13-14
Voting Record -- box 14
Interregnum: November 1954 - April 1955 -- box 15
Hoover Commission, 1953-1955 -- box 15
Philippines Ambassadorship, 1955-1956 -- box 16
United States Court of Military Appeals, 1956-1976 -- boxes 17-21 and 25 (part)
Correspondence -- boxes 17-18, 25
Public Addresses -- boxes 18-19
Topical Files -- boxes 19-21, 25
Inter-Parliamentary Union, 1949-1972 -- box 21
Clippings -- box 22
Photographs -- boxes 23-25 and oversize folder
Sound Recordings -- box 25
Myrtle Ferguson Papers -- box 26
The Homer Ferguson collection has been divided into eleven series based primarily upon the important phases of his public life: Personal; Circuit Judgeship; Senate Career; Interregnum: November 1954 - April 1955; Hoover Commission; Philippine Ambassadorship; United States Court of Military Appeals; Inter-Parliamentary Union; Photographs, Sound Recordings, and Myrtle Ferguson Papers.
Courts.; Crime.; East Asia.; Elections -- Michigan -- 1948.; Elections -- Michigan -- 1954.; Judges -- United States.; Michigan -- Politics and government -- 1939-1945.; Michigan -- Politics and government -- 1946-1960.; Pearl Harbor (Hawaii), Attack on, 1941.; Philippines -- History -- 1946-1986.; Travelers.; United States -- Defenses.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1933-1953.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1953-1961.; Far East.; Forts and fortifications.; Housing.; Inter-American Highway.; Military facilities.; Philippines -- History -- 1946-1986.; Political elections -- 1954.; Politics and government.; Racism.; Saint Lawrence Seaway.; Travel.; Willow Run (Mich.); World War, 1939-1945.; Albums.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Crime.; Criminal courts.; Philippines -- Anniversaries, etc.; Philippines -- History -- 1946-1986.; Trials (Fraud) -- Michigan -- Wayne County.; Trials (Military offenses) -- United States.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989.; Barkley, Alben William, 1877-1956.; Beard, Charles Austin, 1874-1948.; Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.; Hughes Aircraft Company.; McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957.; Pearson, Drew, 1897-1969.; Republican Party (Mich.); United States. Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of the Government (1953-1955); United States. Court of Military Appeals.; United States. Congress. Senate.; Wayne County (Mich.). One-Man Grand Jury (1939-1942); Willow Run Bomber Plant.; Aircraft Parts Production Corporation (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Chrysler Corporation.; Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.; Ferguson, Myrtle.; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Hughes, Howard, 1905-1976.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Inter-parliamentary Union.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Magsaysay, Ramon, 1907-1957.; McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957.; Potter, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1916-1979.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854-); Taft, Robert A. (Robert Alphonso), 1889-1953.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; United States. Army.; United States. Congress. Senate.; United States. Court of Military Appeals.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Ferguson, Myrtle.; United States. Court of Military Appeals.; Wayne County (Mich.). One-Man Grand Jury (1939-1942); Ferguson, Homer, 1889-1982.
- Personal
  The Personal series (scattered dates; 7 folders) includes biographical data, materials pertaining to membership in various organizations, and correspondence with and regarding family members and friends.
  - Biographical Materials (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (mostly greetings and condolences to/from other prominent individuals) (Box 1)
  - Family
    - General (Box 1)
    - Beltz Family (Ferguson's daughter and son-in-law) (Box 1)
    - Hines, Mercia (Ferguson's sister: materials concerning estate settlement) (Box 1)
    - Dragutin, Rausan (Ferguson's god-son: correspondence with and about), 2 folders (Box 1)
- Circuit Judgeship: One-Man Grand Jury, 1939-1941; 0.3 linear feet, 35 phonograph records
  The Circuit Judgeship: One-Man Grand Jury series (1939-1941; 0.3 linear ft. and 35 sound discs) is comprised of materials related to Ferguson's service as a One-Man grand jury. Of primary importance and comprising the bulk of the series are the court transcripts of investigations of Detroiters, including Mayor Richard Reading, many of whom were involved in gambling rackets. The transcripts do not comprise a complete set, but are valuable in painting a graphic picture of the bribing of police officers, the workings of the numbers game, and the running of bookmaking establishments in Wayne County. Ferguson's own reminiscences are interesting, but very brief and frequently based on newspaper accounts.
  - General (includes Ferguson's own reminiscences, "Fish In My Boots"; miscellaneous correspondence; affidavits; etc.), 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Court Transcripts
    - Milton Behrendt Case, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Richard Reading Case, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (pages missing)
    - Carl Brooks, John Bitonti, et al. Case, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Richard Connell, et al. Case (Box 2)
    - John Miller, Zigmund Makericz Case (Box 2)
    - Elmer Ryan, et al. Case, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Transcript Pages (Box 2)
    - Phonograph records of statements taken for Wayne County graft grand jury (Box 2)
      (35 discs in 1 carrying case located separately)
- Senate Career, 1942-1954; 13.5 linear feet
  The largest of the series in the collection is that related to Ferguson's Senate Career (1942-1954; 13.5 linear ft.) and includes six subseries: Committees; Correspondence; Legislative Record; Public Addresses; Topical Files; and Voting Record.
  - Committees
    Under the Committees heading, the researcher will find materials that reflect the investigative side of Homer Ferguson. Organized alphabetically by committee, the materials are those collected or issued by Ferguson during the many senatorial investigations of which he was a part. The researcher will find correspondence; government documents; reports; statements; news releases; handwritten notes; and transcripts of hearings, in varying degrees throughout the files, the majority of which pertain to Ferguson's membership on the Special Committee Investigating the National Defense Program, and the Joint Committee on the Investigation of the Pearl Harbor Attack.
    - Appropriations
      - Bradley, Omar (re:, 1950 testimony before Committee and subsequent news leaks to Drew Pearson) (Box 2)
      - Grain Speculation (Box 2)
      - Trips
        - Trip Around the World, 1949 (Box 2)
          (includes "Senator's Notes")
        - Miscellaneous, 1949-1952 (Box 2)
          (includes handwritten notes on Far East)
      - Subcommittees
        - Armed Services (re: Thule Air Force Base) (Box 2)
        - Commodity Speculation material re: Edwin Pauley, 1948 (Box 2)
        - Foreign Economic Cooperation, 1952 (Box 2)
          (committee agent and mission chief reports)
        - State Department (mostly re: loyalty investigations) (Box 2)
    - Expenditures in the Executive Department: Senate Investigations Subcommittee
      - General (Box 2)
      - Koch, Ilsa (Box 2)
      - Office of Education (Box 2)
      - Remington, William R. (re: loyalty investigation) (Box 2)
      - Surplus Property (Box 2)
    - Investigations
      - Material re: general rules and procedures for committees and subcommittees (Box 2)
    - Judiciary
      - Attendance Record (Box 2)
      - Senate Internal Security Subcommittee
        - General (Box 2)
        - Institute of Pacific Relations (Box 2)
    - National Defense Program (Special Committee Investigating the National Defense Program)
      - Correspondence
        (see also Topical Files)
        The correspondence portion of the National Defense Program files is comprised of both incoming and outgoing letters and is arranged chronologically by year. The incoming letters are the more interesting and contain letters from citizens describing conditions at various defense plants throughout the country. In addition, there are memoranda from committee counsel, and letters and materials from companies under investigation. The Senator's own correspondence is primarily comprised of letters thanking individuals for sending him information.
        - 1943, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - 1944 (Box 3)
        - 1945 (Box 3)
        - 1946, 2 folders (Box 3)
        - 1947 (Box 3)
        - 1948 (Box 3)
      - Topical Files
        The Topical Files, arranged alphabetically, also contain correspondence as well as the types of materials mentioned above. Ferguson's views regarding the investigations undertaken and the individuals and companies involved can be partially determined from the files, but are often only broadly stated, and need to be supplemented by the Committee's published reports. The Topical Files may be helpful to the researcher with specific interest in one of the many areas that was investigated by the Committee. There are, for example, extensive files on the Hughes Corporation; highways; and the Willow Run Bomber Plant.
        - Aeronautics (Box 3)
        - Aircraft and Aviation, 2 folders (Box 3)
          (see also Curtiss-Wright Corporation)
        - Alaska (Box 3)
          (includes materials re: Canol project; military operations; highway system; and postwar land settlement)
        - Aluminum (Box 3)
          (correspondence re: postwar plant disposition--includes letter from Stuart Symington)
        - Army Depots (mostly re: investigation of Fort Bliss, El Paso, Texas), 1944 (Box 3)
        - Barges (Box 4)
          (mostly background materials and exhibits; some correspondence)
        - Braniff Airways (Box 4)
          (three memoranda on aspects of Braniff airmail operations prepared for Ferguson by committee staff member)
        - Canol Oil Project, 2 folders (Box 4)
          (background reports, analyses, and correspondence, including Harold Ickes letter.)
          (see also Alaska)
        - Carbon Black, 2 folders (Box 4)
          (correspondence; committee report; exhibits; briefs; memoranda)
        - Coal (Box 4)
          (mostly citizen correspondence re: shortage)
        - Cigarettes (material re: shortage), 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Curtiss-Wright Corporation (Box 4)
          (see also Aircraft and Aviation)
        - Detroit Tools, 4 folders (Box 4)
        - Engineering Services, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Executive Sessions (Box 4)
          (miscellaneous minutes dealing with a variety of Committee related topics)
        - Farm Machinery (Box 5)
          (primarily correspondence, lists of questions, and prepared answers)
        - Garrson, Henry (Box 5)
          (correspondence and Garrson statement re: investigation of Andrew J. May, Henry Garrson and Murray Garrson, et al)
        - Guatemala (Box 5)
          (notes to Ferguson re: Disposal of Finca "El Porvenir," Cinchona (Quinine) Plantation in Guatemala)
        - Highways (Box 5)
          (mostly correspondence re: Alcan and Pan-American highways)
        - Hotels (material re: Army and Navy use and acquisition of Florida hotels) (Box 5)
        - Housing (Box 5)
          (see also "Willow Run")
        - Hughes Aircraft Company
          - General, 7 folders (Box 5)
            (interesting material re: flying boat project controversy)
          - Wiretapping Controversy (Box 5)
        - Intelligence Activities, Foreign (Box 5)
          (letter from Ferguson to James Mead describing the need for investigation)
        - Inter-American Highway (Box 5)
          (includes interesting letter to/from Nelson Rockefeller)
          (see also "Highways")
        - Labor Reports (drafts of Committee reports) (Box 5)
        - Littell, Norman (Box 5)
          (re: his resignation as Assistant Attorney General)
        - Magee, Harry (Committee field investigator-miscellaneous reports) (Box 5)
        - Magnesium, 3 folders (Box 6)
        - Manpower
          - 1944 (Box 6)
            (mostly correspondence)
          - 1945
            - January 1945, 2 folders (Box 6)
            - February 1945 (Box 6)
            - March 1945 (Box 6)
            - April-July 1945 (Box 6)
            - Navy Yards, 2 folders (Box 6)
            - Textiles (Box 6)
              (mostly testimony and background materials)
        - May, Andrew J. (Box 6)
          (see also "Henry Garrson")
        - Meyers, Bennett E. (Box 6)
          (citizen mail and Stuart Symington statement regarding Meyers' war profiteering)
        - Military Government in Europe (Box 6)
          (interesting material re: controversy over Committee counsel's report)
        - Motor Equipment (Box 7)
        - Navy Contracts (Box 7)
        - Newsprint (correspondence and memoranda), 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Pipelines (Box 7)
        - Remington-Rand and Schick Corporations (Box 7)
        - Saudi Arabia Oil Imports (Box 7)
        - South America (Box 7)
          (see also "Highways," and "Inter-American Highway")
        - Subjects Investigated (Box 7)
          (list of subjects investigated by committee in which Ferguson participated)
        - Sugar (Box 7)
        - Surplus Property, 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Tank Arsenal (mostly correspondence) (Box 7)
        - Tool and Die Companies (Box 7)
        - Transportation (Box 7)
        - Trips:, 1945
          - Caribbean (mostly background material) (Box 7)
          - European (Box 7)
          - West Coast (Box 7)
        - Tucker Corporation (Box 7)
          (material related to its acquisition of Chicago Dodge Chrysler Plant and Clippings re: alleged payoffs to Ferguson)
        - Willow Run Bomber Plant
          - General, 2 folders (Box 7)
            (mostly correspondence and reports related to plant conditions; includes materials on transportation, manpower, and proposed shopping center)
          - Housing, 2 folders (Box 7)
            (includes information on transportation)
        - Wright Aeronautical Corporation (Box 7)
        - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Pearl Harbor (Joint Committee on the Investigation of the Pearl Harbor Attack)
      The Pearl Harbor Committee files should be used in conjunction with the material published by the Committee in 1946. The researcher may, in fact, find that many of Ferguson's documents are part of the published record, although an effort has been made to cull them from the files.
      - Correspondence, Undated
        The correspondence is arranged chronologically by month and year, and is mostly citizen mail, the more important exceptions to which are noted on the contents list.
        - 1944
          - May-June 1944 (Box 8)
            (includes letter to/from Army Judge Advocate General)
          - July-August 1944 (Box 8)
          - September-October 1944 (Box 8)
            (includes letters to/from Secretaries of War and Navy)
          - November-December 1944 (Box 8)
        - 1945
          - January-August 1945 (Box 8)
          - September 1945, 2 folders (Box 8)
          - October 1945 (Box 8)
            (includes correspondence with Committee Counsel and Secretary, Republican Steering Committee)
          - November-December 1945 (Box 8)
            (includes correspondence with Committee Counsel and other non-citizen type mail)
        - 1946
          - January 1946 (Box 8)
          - February 1946 (Box 8)
          - March-April 1946 (Box 8)
          - May-August 1946 (Box 8)
      - Source Documents
        - Government documents (mostly) to which the committee had access, 5 folders (Box 9)
      - Topical Files
        The Topical Files, arranged alphabetically contain interesting material but are not particularly revealing of Ferguson's own views of the Committee's work. His handwritten notes are fragmentary, and appear to have been written primarily during the Committee's hearings. They hint at what the Senator found of interest, but not why, and at times they merely take the form of questions directed at particular individuals. In the Charles Beard file there is very interesting correspondence between Ferguson, Beard, and Beard's nephew, George H. E. Smith (Secretary of the Republican Steering Committee), regarding Beard's involvement with the committee work of Ferguson. Many of the documents collected by Ferguson regarding individuals and aspects of the investigation are interesting in and of themselves (see, for example, Cordell Hull and Frank Knox), but, again, the researcher should first become familiar with the published material.
        - Aircraft Warning (miscellaneous documents) (Box 9)
        - Appropriations, Military (letter and chart re: period), 1933-1941 (Box 9)
        - Barkley, Alben (typewritten remarks re: Barkley's meeting with FDR), August 18, 1941 (Box 9)
          ("Make a file and mark it if Barkley Resignes (sic)" notation at top)
        - Beard, Charles A. (Box 9)
          (includes interesting correspondence re: Ferguson and the Committee)
        - Bellinger, Patrick (Box 9)
          (statement before Committee, and Ferguson notes)
        - Bicknell, George (Box 9)
          (mostly lists of questions, and affidavits)
        - Blue Plan (Box 9)
        - Bratton, Rufus S. (Box 9)
          (lists of questions, summaries of testimony, Ferguson notes)
        - Brink, Francis G. (list of questions) (Box 9)
        - Butler, Nicholas (Box 9)
          (re: his 1933 conversation with Japanese envoy)
        - Chronologies, Events Leading up to Attack, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - Clausen, Henry C. (Box 9)
          (material re: his investigation of Pearl Harbor attack)
        - Codes (Box 9)
        - Committee Counsel, 2 folders (Box 9)
          (correspondence and memoranda: mostly requests for information)
        - Crowley, James (Box 9)
          (correspondence re: his negative reaction to the committee minority report and subsequent radio broadcast)
        - Davis, Forrest (Box 9)
          (list of questions re: his book How War Came)
        - Dewey, Thomas (Box 9)
          (includes copies of interesting correspondence from General Marshall to Dewey re: code deciphering)
        - Dolan, P.A. (incoming correspondence) (Box 9)
        - Dooman, Eugene (Box 9)
          (memo to Ferguson re: informal negotiations between U.S. and Japan prior to attack)
        - Edgers, Dorothy (Box 9)
          (testimony re: her work as a translator)
        - Flynn, John T (Box 9)
        - Forrestal, James (list of questions) (Box 9)
        - G-2 Military Intelligence Estimates (Box 9)
        - Gerow, L.T. (statements, notes, lists of questions) (Box 10)
        - Gillette, Guy M (Box 10)
        - Glassford, William A. (list of questions) (Box 10)
        - Glover, C.D. (list of questions) (Box 10)
        - Grew, Raymond (mostly lists of questions, and handwritten notes) (Box 10)
        - Grunert, Lt. Gen. (lists of questions) (Box 10)
        - Hart, Thomas C (Box 10)
        - Herron, Charles D (Box 10)
        - Hiranuma Proposal (Box 10)
        - Hornbeck, Stanley (Box 10)
        - Hull, Cordell, 2 folders (Box 10)
          (lists of questions; notes; testimony; copies of correspondence between Owen Roberts and Hull; copies of correspondence between Charles Beard and Owen Brewster)
        - Inglis, Thomas B. (Box 10)
          (list of questions, and statement)
        - Ingersol, R.E. (handwritten questions) (Box 10)
        - Jones, E. Stanley (Box 10)
          (Protestant missionary alleged to be involved in peace talks in 1941)
        - Kimmel, Husband E. (Box 10)
          (handwritten notes and questions; statement; documents)
        - King, Admiral (typewritten notes and questions) (Box 10)
        - Knox, Frank (Box 10)
          ("Report By The Secretary of The Navy To The President" (post December 7, 1941), and Eugene Dooman report of1940 conference with Knox, et al)
        - Kramer, A.D. (Box 10)
          (mostly documents, handwritten notes, and questions)
        - Leavell, John H. (Box 10)
          (correspondence and documents re:1941 oil situation in Dutch East Indies)
        - McCollum, A.H. (Box 10)